At long last, the Civil War is over, and
that means it's time for the era of
reconstruction. And I'd love to tell you
that the war itself settled all the
problems between the North and the
South. And that reconstruction was like
the bonfire on the last night of summer
camp where everybody cries and talks
about how much they love each other. But
it turned out it was more like a bonfire
where everybody picked up the burning
logs and started throwing them at each
other. So, I reckon we ought to talk
about it. And if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay. Now, the first thing you need to
know is that there were two major
competing plans for how the process of
reconstruction should play out. And at
the highest level, the main difference
between the two plans is how each one
viewed the defeated southern states.
First was Abraham Lincoln's 10% plan.
And this plan was very lenient and set
the bar pretty low for the southern
states to reenter the union. And that's
because Lincoln's view of southern
secession was that it was never a
constitutional possibility to begin
with. Therefore, by Lincoln's reckoning,
the southern states never actually broke
away and formed their own nation, but
rather they were just rebellious states
that remained in the Union throughout
the war. So even as early as 1863,
Lincoln was working with his advisers on
a plan to rebuild after the war. And he
laid out those plans in the proclamation
of amnesty and reconstruction, which
came to be known as the 10% plan. And it
basically had two requirements. First,
it declared that a state could assume
its rightful place in the Union when 10%
of its eligible voters pledged an oath
of loyalty to the United States. And by
the way, those were the voters who were
eligible to vote in 1860. And then the
second requirement is that the state had
to agree to abolish slavery. And of
course there were other nuances and it
was a little more complicated than that.
But on the whole, Lincoln's plan for
reuniting the North and South was
exceedingly lenient. But the rival plan
was not so lenient. So a group of
radical Republicans in Congress did not
view the southern states as longlost
family members, but rather as conquered
foes who needed to be punished. And as a
reminder, the radical Republicans were
the ones who supported abolition and
civil rights for black Americans. And so
viewing the southern states in this way,
these Republicans laid out a plan for
reconstruction that required a more
heavy-handed approach. And needless to
say, the bar was much higher. To that
end, in 1864, Congress passed the Wade
Davis bill, which like Lincoln's plan,
required a state to abolish slavery. But
it also mandated that a majority of
southern voters, which is to say 51%,
pledge oaths of loyalty to the United
States. Now, Lincoln ultimately killed
the bill with a pocket veto because he
believed that it would destroy the
delicate political relationships that he
had worked to maintain among moderates
and in the border states. And in case
you don't remember, the border states
were made up of four slave states that
had remained in the Union. And because
Lincoln believed that keeping these
slave states in the Union was crucial to
a northern victory in the war, he didn't
want to press them too hard on the
slavery issue and send them running for
the Confederacy. Anyway, the point is
the plan laid out by the radical
Republicans represented a desire for
reconstruction to be carried out with
overwhelming federal power to the
detriment of state power. Now, before I
tell you which plan won the day, let me
quickly mention that if you need help
getting an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May, you might want to
check out my A Bush Heimler review
guide, which has everything you need to
study as fast as possible. And that link
awaits your little clicky finger down in
the description below. Okay, so whether
Lincoln's plan would have worked better
than the congressional plan, we're never
going to know because in April of 1865,
Lincoln was assassinated. He was
attending a play at Forge Theater and a
Confederate sympathizer named John Wils
Booth entered Lincoln's box and shot
him. And Lincoln died the next morning,
literally 6 days after the Civil War had
ended. And so according to the
Constitution, if the president dies,
then his vice president assumes the
office. And in this case, it was Andrew
Johnson. Now, if Lincoln's spirit animal
was a wisened owl, then Johnson's was
more like a drunken racist hyena.
Anyway, Lincoln added Johnson to the
ticket in his bid for re-election in
1864, not because they agreed with each
other on all that much. I mean, Johnson
was a pro-UN southern Democrat from
Tennessee, who had himself been an
enslaveer. But since, like I mentioned
before, Lincoln was deeply concerned
about keeping the border states in the
Union, making Johnson as vice president
was a way to satisfy the interests of
those states. But regardless, once he
became president, Johnson chneled his
drunk hyena energy and was pretty dang
reckless in executing reconstruction
plans, which led to a bitter rivalry
between him and Congress. Now, to be
fair, Johnson did attempt to carry out
Lincoln's 10% plan, but since he seemed
to lack any skill to persuade and
negotiate with congressional
Republicans, it did not go well.
Furthermore, Johnson just seemed to view
the whole process of reconstruction as
kind of an annoyance that he wanted to
complete as fast as possible and let
southerners rebuild and tend to their
own affairs. In fact, Johnson seemed to
be using his power as president to enact
personal vengeance on elite southern
planters. You see, even though he had
been an enslaver himself, Johnson grew
up poor and resented the political and
social control wielded by the planter
elite in the South. Therefore, while
Johnson administered mass pardons to
Southerners who took the required
loyalty oath, he required wealthy
planters to petition him personally to
secure their pardon. It seemed like he
was just giddy to have all this power
over the elite planters, and he seemed
to relish making them come to beg for
their citizenship. What I'm trying to
say is Johnson was using his
presidential power to carry out his
personal vengeance and that ultimately
made a significant contribution to the
failure of reconstruction and all the
national griefs that followed. Anyway,
only 8 months after the war had ended,
Johnson believed that the goals of
reconstruction had been accomplished and
it was time to move on. However,
congressional Republicans strongly
disagreed on account of the southern
states looked an awful lot like they did
before the Civil War with the exception
that slavery was now abolished. For
example, newly formed state legislatores
had elected former Confederate leaders
to guide policy matters, and some even
sent Confederate leaders to Congress.
And maybe the craziest example here is
that Georgia elected Alexander Stevens
to the House of Representatives. And I
hope that name rings a bell because
Stevens was the vice president of the
stinking Confederacy. Like, he was the
guy who gave his cornerstone speech,
reveling in the fact that the
foundational principle on which the
Confederacy was erected and sustained
was a fundamental inequality between the
white and black races. This is the guy
the Georgians sent to represent them in
Congress. Like what? Additionally,
several southern states passed a series
of black codes that severely restricted
the civil rights of black Americans,
which in some cases differed very little
from the conditions of slavery. So the
point is, President Johnson looked at
all those developments and was like,
"Well, all right. South looks pretty
good to me. Let's move on." But the
radical Republicans were having none of
it, and they were about to take control
of reconstruction quick, fast, and in a
hurry. So, in the midterm elections of
1866, radical Republicans won big time
and as a result had twothirds of the
seats in Congress. And in case you're a
little fuzzy on Article 1, Section 7 of
the Constitution, 2/3 is the amount
needed for Congress to override a
presidential veto. And with that power
now in their hands, radical Republicans
were ready to take reconstruction away
from the president and make it an
entirely congressional process.
Moreover, they sought to continue
reconstruction by means of federal power
since allowing states such leniency was
clearly not getting results under the
turd Andrew Johnson. And then more
moreover, these Republicans further
consolidated their power by refusing to
seat former Confederates who had been
elected to Congress by the southern
states. And there were two strategies
they used to complete their vision of
reconstruction. First was the passage of
three amendments to the constitution.
The 13th amendment formerly abolished
slavery in the United States and it was
ratified in 1865. Now, as I mentioned
before, ratifying this amendment was a
requirement for southern states
re-entering the union. And technically,
this amendment was ratified before the
whole congressional takeover of
reconstruction. However, as I mentioned
earlier, it turned out that the southern
states could ratify an amendment
abolishing slavery and then go right
back to stripping black southerners of
their rights like we saw with the
passage of the Black Coast. Anyway, the
next two amendments sought to correct
this kind of nonsense. The 14th
Amendment was ratified in 1868 and
established birthright citizenship for
the formerly enslaved while also
mandating that American civil rights
could not be infringed upon by states.
And that last part is important because
prior to the passage of this amendment,
the civil liberties outlined in the Bill
of Rights were only protected from
federal intrusion, not state intrusion.
And so this amendment was important to
the Republicans since some of the major
civil rights legislation they had passed
was vetoed or otherwise frustrated by an
embittered and sassy President John. For
example, they passed two civil rights
acts which defined the terms of
citizenship and outlawed racial
discrimination. But seeing how easily
such legislation could be ignored and
thwarted, Republicans worked to include
the substance of these laws into the
Constitution itself where they would be
much harder to sidestep. And then the
15th Amendment was ratified in 1870
which guaranteed voting rights for black
men. And yes, just black men. And I'll
tell you more about that in a moment.
Okay. And then the second tactic
Republicans used to carry out
reconstruction was to impose martial law
in the South. So in 1867, they passed
the Military Reconstruction Act, which
divided the South into five military
districts. Soon after, federal troops
were sent to occupy the South in order
to ensure that the requirements for
reconstruction were being upheld and
that racial discrimination resulting
from policies like black codes could not
occur. And as a result of these
heavy-handed tactics, all the states of
the former Confederacy had met the
requirements and rejoined the Union by
1870. But they resented such
disciplinary tactics. Okay, now come
back to the 15th Amendment for a moment.
Remember that it recognized the right of
black men to vote, and this was pretty
universally cheered by America's black
population. But as it turned out, some
women's rights advocates were not so
giddy about it. So recall that women
played a significant role in the
abolitionist movement before the war.
And then after the war, abolitionists,
many women included, created the
American Equal Rights Association. And
its members worked to ensure that
emancipated black Americans had equal
access to their rights. However, when
the association meant to consider how
best to support the ratification of the
15th Amendment, things got ugly quick,
fast, and in a hurry. That's because the
15th Amendment protected voting rights
from racial discrimination, but not
gender discrimination. So women like
Elizabeth Katie Stanton argued against
the 15th Amendment because she believed
that by furthering the rights of black
men, the rights of women would be
further ignored and eroded. And she even
used racial arguments to make her point.
She said that it was an outrage that
even the poorest and least educated
black, Irish, Chinese, or German
citizens could vote. Like, shouldn't the
vote of an educated white woman count
more than that? However, on the other
side of the debate were folks like
Frederick Douglas, who argued that
extending the franchise to black men was
a necessity and would likely speed up
the process for opening the franchise to
women. Well, as it turned out, Stanton
and her allies Susan B. Anthony refused
to back down on this issue and broke
away to form the National Women's
Suffrage Association. And this all
female organization protested loudly
against the ratification of the 15th
Amendment. But once it passed, they got
to work advocating for another
constitutional amendment that would
recognize women's right to vote. And I'm
sad to tell you that it would be
something like 50 years before that
became a reality, but we'll have to pick
that up again in unit 6. Okay, you can
click here to watch my other videos from
unit 5, or you can click here to get my
A Push Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. I'm glad you came around and
I'll catch you on the flip-flop.